<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE riscos-prm PUBLIC "-//Gerph//DTD PRM documentation 1.02//EN"
                            "http://www.movspclr.co.uk/dtd/102/prm.dtd">

<riscos-prm>
<chapter title="The MimeMap module">

<section title="Introduction">
<p>
In order to determine the operations which can be performed on data, a
system of 'typing' is used. On different operating systems and environments,
different typing systems are employed:
</p>

<p>
<list>
  <item><p>Under RISC OS, the typing system is known as 'file types' and is
determined by numeric identifiers (the filetype of an object) in strict
range (0-4095).</p></item>

  <item><p>Under DOS and Windows-like systems, the type system is known as an
'file extension' (sometimes known as a 'dot extension') and is determined by
a string - traditionally of three characters - appended to the
filename.</p></item>

  <item><p>Under unix-like systems, the type system varies but most commonly a
similar system to that employed by DOS and Windows is used, or a system
based on the content of the file.</p></item>

  <item><p>On Apple machines, the type is a fixed length binary identifier (8
bytes), split into two fields (4 bytes each) - the vendor identifier and the
file type.</p></item>

</list>
</p>

<p>With this diverse selection of type systems in use and in order to try to
standardise the manner in which such types are identified, a system of
'media types' (also known as the 'content type') was developed. This is
colloqially known as the 'MIME type', from its use in the most widespread
use of its application, Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions. This media
type categorises the data by category, providing a number of general
categories into which data falls (for example, text or video). </p>

<p>The MimeMap module provides a central service for mapping between most
of the types available. Of those described above, the MimeMap module does
not presently cater for file identification by its contents.</p>

</section>

<section title="Overview">
<p>
When the module is initialised (either on being loaded, or during boot up)
it reads the file <reference type="sysvar" name="Inet$MimeMappings" /> and
stores the parsed file internally. If the system variable is changed, or the
module is explicitly requested, the old version will be discarded and the
file reparsed. </p>

<p>
The MimeMap module can handle 5 different file typing schemes:
</p>
<p>
<list>
  <item><p>RISC OS file type by number, eg &hex;FFF</p></item>
  <item><p>RISC OS file type by name, eg Text</p></item>
  <item><p>Media type string, eg text/plain</p></item>
  <item><p>File extension string, eg .txt</p></item>
  <item><p>Mac type/creator pair, eg "ttxtTEXT"</p></item>
</list>
</p>

<p>
Any type can be converted to any other type by the module should such a
mapping exist in the file. Dependant on the settings in the MimeMap
configuration, certain conversions may not be possible. For some of the
conversions, wildcards (fields identifying multiple potential matches) may
be available.
</p>

<subsection title="Using the module">

<p>
In order to ensure that type conversion is performed in a consistent and
maintainable manner, it is recommended that type conversions are - whereever
possible - performed through the MimeMap module. Typical applications which
would require translations to be performed would be network file transfers
(for example remote filing systems, FTP or HTTP transfers), non-native
hardware transfers (for example CD-ROM data, floppy discs), and collated
file processing (for example MIME format messages such as email).
</p>

<p>As supplied, the RISC OS filing systems DOSFS and CDFS support the use of the MimeMap module.</p>

</subsection>

</section>

<section title="Technical details">

<subsection title="Type formats">
<p>Because the types supported by the MimeMap module are represented in different ways,
a 'type format' is used to distinguish between each of the types in SWI calls.
<value-table head-number="Value" head-name="Name" head-value="Meaning">
 <value number="0" name="MMM_TYPE_RISCOS">RISC OS file type passed as an 32
 bit number</value>

 <value number="1" name="MMM_TYPE_RISCOS_STRING">RISC OS file type passed as
 a pointer to a zero terminated string</value>

 <value number="2" name="MMM_TYPE_MIME">MIME content type passed as a
 pointer to a zero terminated string</value>

 <value number="3" name="MMM_TYPE_DOT_EXTN">File extension (without the
 preceeding period) as a pointer to a zero terminated string</value>

 <value number="4" name="MMM_TYPE_MAC">Mac type as a pointer to a 8 byte block</value>
</value-table>
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection title="Type representation">
<p>The types listed above are represented textually within the MimeMap database
file and as parameters to <reference type="command" name="MimeMap" />. The following
sections describe each of the types as used in these locations.
</p>

<category title="Media types">
<p>
Media types are supplied in the form 'major/minor'. The format and meaning
is defined in RFCs 2045-2049 (Request For Comments, the main repository of
internet standards) and a database of registered media types
is maintained by IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers Authority).
</p>
</category>

<category title="RISC OS type number and name">
<p>
Whilst both the type name and number are provided in the MimeMap database
and as a translation with <reference type="swi" name="MimeMap_Translate" />,
only the number is retained by the module. This allows the type name to be
undefined initially and values to be provided when they are available though
the standard file type naming variables.
</p>
<p>
Type numbers may take any value from &hex;000 to &hex;FFF, as defined by
the standard file typing system. The special value &hex;1000 is not used
by the MimeMap module.
</p>
</category>

<category title="Dot extensions">
<p>
Dot extensions are preceeded by a period ('<code type="format">.</code>')
character when passed in the *MimeMap command and in the MimeMap file. In
the MimeMap file, multiple extensions can be supplied indicating that
multiple extensions are used for a single type.
</p>
</category>

<category title="Mac type names">
<p>
Mac types are specified in the form: "XXXXxxxx" where XXXX is the filetype
and xxxx is the vendor type. ? can be used as a single character wildcard.
\? means a literal ?. \t, \v, \n, \r have their usual meanings (9, 11, 10 and
13 respectively). \DD (where DD describes 2 hexadecimal digits) represents
the character with ASCII code &hex;DD.
</p>
<p>
There is a default Mac mapping defined, where "&hex;DDDAcrn" maps to filetype
&hex;DDD (for hexadecimal digits DDD). This vendor name is registered with Apple.
Within Mac mappings, the least number of wildcards is matched if multiple
matches are possible.
</p>
<p>
Mac mappings must be enclosed in double quotes (") when passed to the
*MimeMap command, and in the MimeMap file.
</p>
</category>
</subsection>

<subsection title="File format">
<p>
The MimeMap file is split into 5 fields to provide the type mappings
database. Entries within the file are searched in the same order in
which they appear, with wildcards matched last. Fields are tab delimited,
and consist of :
</p>

<p>
<code type="format">
&lt;mimetype&gt;
&lt;tab&gt;
&lt;ro-text&gt;
&lt;tab&gt;
&lt;ro-hex&gt;
&lt;tab&gt;
&lt;extensions&gt;
&lt;tab&gt;
&lt;mactype&gt;
</code>
</p>

<p>
<value-table>
  <value number="mimetype">Media type in the form 'major/minor'</value>
  <value number="major">Major component of the media type, or '*' wildcard
                        to match with any major type.</value>
  <value number="minor">Minor component of the media type, or '*' wildcard
                        to match with any minor type.</value>
  <value number="ro-text">Textual form of the 'ro-hex' field for readability
                        purposes</value>
  <value number="ro-hex">Hexadecimal RISC OS type</value>
  <value number="extensions">File extensions, in the form of a period ('.') prefixed,
                        tab separated list of file extensions.</value>
  <value number="mactype">Mac vendor/type string as defined above.</value>
</value-table>
</p>
</subsection>
</section>


<section title="System variables">
<sysvar-definition name="Inet$MimeMappings"
                   description="Defines the filename of the MimeMap database file">
<use>
<p>This variable names the file which will be used to provide mappings
information for the MimeMap module. Assigning a value to this variable
will cause the MimeMap module to re-parse its contents.
</p>
<p>
Usually this variable will take the value <filename>InetDBase:MimeMap</filename>
during normal use. When the system boots, its value will point to a file
in ResourceFS which contains a basic file with simple mappings.
</p>
</use>

<related>
<reference type="command" name="ReadMimeMap" />
<!-- <reference type="swi" name="thingy" /> -->
<!-- <reference type="vector" name="bingleV" /> -->
</related>

</sysvar-definition>
</section>

<section title="SWI calls">
<swi-definition name="MimeMap_Translate"
                number="50B00"
                description="Perform translation between type systems"
                irqs="undefined"
                fiqs="enabled"
                processor-mode="SVC"
                re-entrant="no">

<entry>
 <register-use number="0">Input type format</register-use>
 <register-use number="1">Input type, or pointer to buffer containing type data</register-use>
 <register-use number="2">Output type format</register-use>
 <register-use number="3">Pointer to output type buffer of up to 128 bytes, if required by
   output format</register-use>
</entry>
<exit>
 <register-use number="0-2" state="preserved" />
 <register-use number="3">Result from conversion, or preserved if output data in
   buffer</register-use>
</exit>
<use>
<p>
This SWI is used to access the type mapping database to convert from one type
format to another. The conversion is performed as cleanly as is possible, returning
the most relevant match as provided by the mapping database file.
</p>
<p>
If no mapping can be performed, an error will be returned.
</p>

</use>

<related>
<reference type="command" name="MimeMap" />
</related>

</swi-definition>

<swi-definition name="MimeMap_Configure"
                number="50B01"
                description="Configure the MimeMap module"
                irqs="undefined"
                fiqs="enabled"
                processor-mode="SVC"
                re-entrant="no">

<entry>
 <register-use number="0">Configure type :
  <value-table>
   <value number="0">Re-read MimeMap file</value>
   <value number="other">Reserved</value>
  </value-table>
 </register-use>
</entry>
<use>
<p>
This SWI is used to configure aspects of MimeMap type conversion. At present, only
a single reason code is provided; that for forcing a re-read of the MimeMap file.
</p>

<p>
If the reason code is not recognised, an error is returned.
</p>

</use>

<related>
<reference type="command" name="ReadMimeMap" />
</related>

</swi-definition>
</section>



<section title="*Commands">
<command-definition name="MimeMap"
                    description="Perform a translation and display the results">
<syntax>
 <text>&amp;</text><userreplace>type</userreplace>
</syntax>
<syntax>
 <text>.</text><userreplace>extension</userreplace>
</syntax>
<syntax>
 <userreplace>major</userreplace>/<userreplace>minor</userreplace>
</syntax>
<syntax>
 <userreplace>typename</userreplace>
</syntax>
<syntax>
 <text>"</text><userreplace>mactype</userreplace><text>"</text>
</syntax>

<!-- parameters -->
<parameter name="type">Hexadecimal value of RISC OS type</parameter>
<parameter name="extension">File extension type</parameter>
<parameter name="major">Major category of media type</parameter>
<parameter name="minor">Minor type of media type</parameter>
<parameter name="typename">Textual form of RISC OS type</parameter>
<parameter name="mactype">Mac type mapping string as used in the configuration file</parameter>

<use>
<p>
This command is used to display mappings of types in a human readable manner.
It is usually used as a aid for debugging the mapping of types. If issued with
no parameters, it will list all the known types.</p>
</use>

<example>
<command>*MimeMap application/octet-stream</command>
<command>*MimeMap &amp;1AD</command>
</example>

<related>
<reference type="swi" name="MimeMap_Translate" />
</related>

</command-definition>



<command-definition name="ReadMimeMap"
                    description="This command causes the MimeMap module to re-read the mappings file.">

<use>
<p>
This command is used to force the MimeMap module to re-read the database
and parse it into internal structures. Although the MimeMap module will
automatically read the database if the system variable changes, if the
file is changed the module should be informed through this command.
</p>
</use>

<example>
<command>*ReadMimeMap</command>
</example>

<related>
<reference type="sysvar" name="Inet$MimeMappings" />
</related>

</command-definition>
</section>


</chapter>



<!-- MetaData -->
<meta>
 <maintainer>
  <email name="RISCOS Ltd" address="developer@riscos.com" />
 </maintainer>
 <disclaimer>
  <import document="http://www.riscos.com/prm/prm-disclaimer.xml" path="root/*" />
  <import document="http://www.riscos.com/prm/amh-disclaimer.xml" path="root/*" />
 </disclaimer>

 <history>
  <revision number="1" author="ROL" title="Extended from ANT release note">
   <change>Added documentation of Mac file type conversion.</change>
  </revision>
  <revision number="2" date="21 Feb 2003" author="ROL" title="Finished file format">
   <change>The file format is now described by the 'code' element.</change>
  </revision>
  <revision number="3" date="21 Mar 2003" author="AMH" title="Fixes">
   <change>Previous version didn't compile. This one does.</change>
  </revision>
  <revision number="4" date="22 Mar 2003" author="ROL" title="Validation">
   <change>Last changes didn't validate at all</change>
  </revision>
 </history>
</meta>
</riscos-prm>
